Okay so for today's דף daf 105 and we're going to start
about one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, about 15 or 18
lines down starting with the word בירקא. beyarka. Now we're in the
middle of discussing what is needed for to wait between meat and
milk. So I want to say two things. First of all yesterday
we talked about the washing of the hands and the cleaning of
the mouth.
I think yesterday I slightly misstated it. According to רש״י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot when it says קינוח kinuach it's both they mention washing
the they meant both wiping the mouth and washing the mouth. תוספות
Tosafot understands that and רש״י Rashi understands it to mean both not
either. That's just important for when we want to do that between
cheese and milk it doesn't mean either it means both. More significantly
the גמרא Gemara
yesterday the גמרא Gemara says מדיח אף מקנח מקנח אף מדיח mediach
af mekaneach mekaneach af mediach so רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both
say that that means both not either.
Besides which the גמרא Gemara earlier spoke about just
wiping washing hands and cleaning off between meat and milk it said
yes chicken not meat. But I said yesterday I sort of framed
it as it was when the cheese was first and the meat
was second. Now that was already a way to reconcile it with
our practice and what we're going to see later. But actually I
should mention and I'll talk about this in a minute after we
read that in the גמרא Gemara if אגור's Iggur original statement was
עוף וגבינה of u-gevina he mentioned עוף of first. If you take
that literally it actually means that even between chicken and cheese chicken
coming first it's enough to just wash your hand and clean your
mouth. Okay so we're going to talk about that today as we
well I don't know but presumably not with meat. And that was
so that but then the גמרא Gemara said sometimes if you look
at your hands you don't have to clean your hands etc. Okay
so that was just a washing and now today we're going to
turn Is it recording?
Yeah I just noticed there's no image there. Maybe it's because it
had you for a long time.
Okay so moving on. Alright so let's take a look. So now
we're going to do about the waiting period. We've discussed about the
washing now we're going to do the waiting period. בעי מיניה רב
אסי מרבי יוחנן ba'ei minei Rav Assi me-Rabbi Yochanan כמה ישהה kama
yisheh and I'm starting with the word ישהה yisheh כמה ישהה בין
בשר לגבינה kama yisheh bein basar le-gevina how long do you have
to wait between meat and milk? אמר ליה ולא כלום amar leh
velo klum not at all. Okay that's a good answer. אמר ליה
amar leh he said back to him איני eini is this really
true? איני
והאמר רב חסדא eini ve-ha-amar Rav Chisda אכל בשר אסור לאכול גבינה
achal basar assur le-echol gevina if you eat meat you can't eat
cheese afterwards גבינה מותר לאכול בשר gevina mutar le-echol basar but if
you eat and here's where we're finally introducing that the order matters
cheese first you can eat meat afterwards. אלא כמה ישהה ela kama
yisheh I said yesterday they didn't drink milk אלא כמה ישהה בין
גבינה לבשר ela kama yisheh bein gevina le-basar so really the question
was how long do you have to wait between cheese and meat?
אמר ליה ולא כלום amar leh velo klum not at all. So
now we're introducing a waiting period and we're saying order matters. So
we'll talk about this in a minute but now we have that
order matters. Now גופא gufa אמר רב חסדא amar Rav Chisda אכל
בשר אסור לאכול גבינה achal basar assur le-echol gevina if you ate
meat first you can't eat cheese גבינה מותר לאכול בשר gevina mutar
le-echol basar cheese first then you can eat meat afterwards without waiting.
Thank you. אמר ליה amar leh he said back גבינה מותר לאכול
בשר אמר ליה רב אחא בר יוסף לרב חסדא gevina mutar le-echol
basar amar leh Rav Acha bar Yosef le-Rav Chisda so רב אחא
בר יוסף Rav Acha bar Yosef said to רב חסדא Rav Chisda
בשר שבין השיניים מהו basar she-bein ha-shinayim mahu let's say you've got
some pieces of meat stuck between your teeth is that considered like
you still have meat in your mouth is presumably the question if
it's just stuck there and it's been there for a while is
how is that does that remain a problem? קרי עליה karei aleih
he said about him about that הבשר עודנו בין שניהם ha-basar odenu
bein sheneihem the meat was still between their teeth. So you see
when it's between your teeth it's still considered meat. Now you could
read that two ways. You could say that therefore when you finally
get that meat out with a toothpick or however you get it
out then you
have to wait a period of time whatever that period of time
is from that moment. Or it might just mean
that while it's between your teeth you can't eat it. The normal
assumption is the latter. It's also then the question about that might
be why although never said in the גמרא Gemara why you have
to
wait but one of the basic explanations is because the meat gets
stuck in your teeth or the taste gets stuck in your mouth
and so on and particularly the meat stuck in your teeth may
be because of this question right here and that's maybe why meat
first is worse than cheese first or milk first cheese first it
doesn't get stuck as much gets digested sooner and so on. So
in the ראשונים Rishonim they basically give two explanations for the purpose
of the waiting period. One is it gets stuck in your mouth
in your teeth and the other is it's very fatty and those
are not as relevant by cheese and therefore that's why meat first
is a bigger problem than cheese first. They try to say a
difference would be between those two approaches which is what if it's
something that you don't chew like let's say it's like chicken soup
or something like that something that wouldn't get between your teeth and
so on but for all intents and purposes we sort of ignore
those distinctions. But anyways they try to connect it into that the
fact that there's this question about stuck between your teeth might be
a signal what the problem is why meat is more problematic first
than cheese first. Now let's talk about how long you have to
wait until now we've just said It's forbidden, but not really forever,
it means immediate. So let's take a look. אמר amar, מר עוקבא
*Amar Mar Ukva*, said מר עוקבא *Mar Ukva*, אנא להא מילתא חלא
בר חמרא לגבי אבא *Ana le-ha milta chala bar chamra legabe abba*.
For this matter, I am like vinegar the son of wine compared
to my father. דאילו אבא כי הוה אכל בשרא האידנא לא הוה
אכל גבינה עד למחר *De-ilu abba ki hava achal bisra idna lo
hava achal gevina ad lemachar*. My father, if he would eat meat
today, he would not eat cheese until tomorrow, עד השתא *ad hashta*,
until the same time. He'd wait a full 24 hours between meat
and cheese. You should all feel very grateful that we are so
lenient. ואילו אנא *Ve-ilu ana*, and I, בהא סעודתא הוא דלא אכילנא
*be-ha seudata hu de-la achilna*, I don't eat it at this meal,
אבל לסעודתא אחריתא אכילנא *aval le-seudata achrita achilna*, I eat it at
another meal. And this is the end of the סוגיא sugya *sugya*
of waiting between meat and milk. So, I eat it at another
what?
What about the first statement that said מותר אכול גבינה *mutar achol
gevina*?
Yeah, cheese first is okay. But now we're talking about
ואילו אכל בשרא *ve-ilu achal bisra*, right, it's גבינה מקודם *gevina mikodem*.
The first piece said cheese first then you can eat meat right
afterwards. No, the first one, no then we reversed it, we reversed
it. רבי Rebbe יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, yeah, we reversed it. We said
it can't be that's true because it has to be reconciled with
the other statement so we reversed it.
Where does it say, where does it say
we reversed רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*? It says אלא *ela*. אלא תני
איפכא בין גבינה לבשר אמר ליה Amar lei, לאו כלום היא *Ela
tani ipcha bein gevina le-vasar amar lei lav klum hi*. Okay, so
anyway, so this is the end of that סוגיא *sugya*. So we
say how much does he wait? He waits from one meal to
the next. Now how much time is there from one meal to
the next? You could take it literally that it's not about time,
it's about the next meal. And that's what תוספות Tosfos, *Tosafot* says.
If you look at a little תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, לסעודתא אחריתא אכילנא
*le-seudata achrita achilna*, לאו דסעודתא שרגילין לעשות אחת שחרית ואחת ערבית *lav
de-seudata she-regilin laasot achat shacharit ve-achat arvit*. Not that it means like
the normal space of meals like one in breakfast and one in
the evening that might be even like even more than six hours.
Anyway, אלא אפילו לאלתר אם סילק השולחן ובירך מותר דלא פליגי רבנן
*ela afilu lealtar im silek ha-shulchan ve-veirach mutar de-lo pligi rabanan*. It's
about a different meal, it's not about time. So if you finish
one meal, clear away the table, made a ברכת המזון *birkat ha-mazon*,
whatever you did, then you have your next meal, you could eat
cheese at your immediate next meal. And that's what תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*
says. The רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* says you wait the time it takes
the average time between meals. He says כשש שעות ke-sheish sha'ot *ke-shesh
shaot*, approximately six hours. He uses the כ *kaf*, which is important
for some people, like six hours. That's what the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*
says. So this leads to the waiting period between meat and milk,
with the first of the big מחלוקת *machloket* אשכנזים Ashkenazim *Ashkenazim* ספרדים
*Sefardim*, which is, is it just a different meal or is it
actually a period of time? Now, the logic, as I said, is
pretty much agreed upon that it's because somehow, and implicit in the
difference between meat first and cheese first, is that the fattiness or
the strings get caught in your teeth and therefore we don't want
that the actual taste of meat in your mouth or the experience
of that meat meal still in your mouth when you're eating the
cheese. Now why, why would a new meal be enough if obviously
that's not cleaning out your mouth? Right, a new meal is just
a new meal, what does that do? So the fact that the
אשכנזים Ashkenazim *Ashkenazim* say a meal is technically enough, in my mind
again, is a clear indication of the point that I made yesterday
which is that it's not really about necessarily about eating, literally having
them together, it's about a rabbinic, you know, a concern that you
might come to cook them together, it's a rabbinic
redefinition of the concept of what does it mean to eat together.
So the same way having one at the table when I'm eating
the other is like I'm eating them together, okay, having the taste
in my mouth or the strands in my mouth and having that
experience, the previous experience of
eating still sort of intertwined with this experience of eating, that's like
I ate them all at the same table, like I ate them
together. If, however, I remove the table, I clean it off, I
בענטש *bentch*, I make a ברכת המזון *birkat ha-mazon*, I start a
new meal, even if I do maybe have some taste in my
mouth, I haven't eaten them together, it's a brand new meal. So
I think particularly in תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* you see that it's about
defining a formal way of defining has it been together or not
together? and therefore a new meal, you know, the taste in the
mouth is not the problem per se. The taste in the mouth
is what connects it and makes it like it was all eaten
together. If, however, I start a new meal then it's like they've
been eaten separately. That is תוספות's Tosafot *Tosafot's* approach. The רמב"ם Rambam
*Rambam*, who requires the space between meals, presumably might be the same
but is just measuring it by time, but presumably is more concerned
about the reality of the taste in your mouth and therefore he
wants to make sure that that gets practically cleaned and starting a
new meal is not sufficient. That's the approach of the רמב"ם Rambam
*Rambam* and those that follow him. Interestingly, where אשכנזים Ashkenazim, *Ashkenazim* we
technically could do a new meal, and by the way, the רמ"א
Rama, *Rema* actually the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch *Shulchan Aruch* rules six
hours like the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*, the רמ"א *Rema* says actually technically
for אשכנזים Ashkenazim *Ashkenazim* a new meal is enough, but then he
sort of brings down the מנהג minhag? *minhag* or whatever or the
חומרא chumra, *chumra* to wait the six hours like the רמב"ם Rambam,
*Rambam*. But as you might know, you know, German Jews and people
that really go by a pure אשכנזי Ashkenazi *Ashkenazi* custom, so three
hours for Germans, who's one hour? No, Dutch. Isn't Dutch three?
No, Dutch is one. Yeah, they do one hour.
One is basically תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, just translating it a little bit
into some. period of time, but it's basically תוספות. Tosafot Three hours
is the hardest to explain, unless I know there's been some research,
unless it was in a place where there was two meals that
were separated by about three hours and you say it is about
time but it's a little bit contingent based on location. Maybe it's
people eat breakfast at nine and twelve, so maybe it's a little
contingent based on location and so on. So there's a whole discussion
about that. There's some that follow the רמב"ם Rambam but try to
use the כשש שעות and they say into the sixth hour, so
they do five hour and a little bit, five hours and a
minute, or some do five and a half hours.
I don't understand where that came from, six hours.
They came from the six hours seemed too hard and
look
at the when time keeping became exact. Before the רמב"ם and the
רמ"א, people started using clocks, right? So you couldn't say sun dial
or whatever.
So that's how it's measured.
So that's
to clear up your saying in general, it should be about six
hours, you shouldn't have to watch your watch. That's an interesting question,
too. How you decide the wait is an interesting question. Ash! By
the way, it's one of those days. There's an interesting question in
the רמב"ם is, what if the רמב"ם ever agrees to something that
was not just about the period of time? Like, let's say, let's
say for example, I went to sleep. I had a midnight snack,
some leftover טשולנט cholent at 2 a.m., and I woke up at
7 a.m., right? Can I have breakfast then? You know, that's really
a separate, completely, you know, psychologically is completely a previous day, right?
But it's not six hours. You know, is six hours still even
for the רמב"ם some degree of a stand-in for a separate meal,
and there might be other ways of achieving it as well. You
know, it's also could be like, you know, so those are like
open-ended questions about that. But there is this basic issue about separating
it. Is it really about removing the physical experience in your mouth,
flossing, mouthwash, etc.? Is it, maybe that suffices? But is that necessary,
or maybe there's another way by just defining it as a new
meal? So that's the first debate.
The other thing I want, I want to finish up with one
or two key points about this. Number two is the thing we
mentioned yesterday about the washing of the hands and the cleaning out
of the mouth. So תוספות, Tosafot there's one way תוספות Tosafot reconciles
it is sort of what I said yesterday without going into the
details, but essentially limiting that to when cheese was first and milk
was first. And that's sort of what we do. You have milk
first, you wash your hands, you clean out your mouth, then you
can go ahead and eat meat right away. However, I mean, there's
some nuances to that, but I'll leave it at that. However, I
should mention that תוספות Tosafot points out a position of רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam and the בה"ג, Behag, which was as if this idea
of a new meal wasn't enough, they actually say that what we
said yesterday was actually the same for if the meat was first.
And that even if the meat was first, you could go ahead
and wash your hands and clean out your mouth, and the fact
that here he had to wait six hours or twenty four hours,
not six or twenty four, his father waited twenty four hours, he
started a new meal, that's if they didn't want to bother washing
their hands and cleaning out their mouth. But, which is a little
funny, my father waited twenty four hours, why shouldn't he wash out
his mouth? But, רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam actually says just to show
you how lenient some Ashkenazic approaches are, that a, either a new
meal no matter how soon after, or b, wash your hands, clean
out your mouth, and then it could be immediately after even if
not a new meal. Either way. But we generally take yesterday's גמרא
Gemara to be about milk first, this גמרא Gemara about meat first,
and even so אשכנזים are still saying that a new meal suffices.
Now, one final thing and then I'll take questions.
What about the cheese? You're noticing cheese here is treated like your
standard milk dish and it's more lenient and there's no waiting period,
etc. The מהר"ם מרוטנבורג, Maharam MiRothenburg, the רבי of the רא"ש Rosh
and the מרדכי, Mordechai, whatever, 13th century major Ashkenazi פוסק, posek, said
that he was once had some cheese and he was eating a
meat meal or whatever and then he realized that some of the
cheese had caught between his teeth. So therefore after that point on
he was strict on himself, not for others, not to wait even
between cheese and meat, but it's only as he said or the
later student said, it was only like the hard cheeses that really
is, you know, very, you know, very fatty and gets caught in
your mouth and so on. From there develops this practice of the
hard cheese and how do you define hard, how moldy and so
on, but the interesting thing is it was never ruled by the
מהר"ם Maharam that way. He just spoke about his own personal practice,
but then it sort of became among some of his followers an
actual הלכה halakha and that's where that comes from, certainly not from
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so that is where we get the whole
idea of the waiting period rule. Some quick questions.
Wait, the ספרדי Sephardi have different cheese? אמן, Amen, yeah.
I really want to know how that sounded. How everybody is not,
but I'm confounded by the idea. I don't think the ספרדי Sephardi
wait to do that.
ספרדי Sephardi what? Wait between
milk and meat? No, I never said that.
Between meat and milk,
of course, yes,
of course.
Oh, I didn't think they had to stay...
You just said that the אשכנזים were the crazy ones. Yeah. Here,
actually the אשכנזים, I know, but
here actually מעיקר הדין me-ikar hadin the
אשכנזים are...
According to the רמב"ם, מקנח mekaneach wouldn't be sufficient?
Or if you eat... Why not? I mean, meaning like the way
you presented it, as I understood it, was that the problem was
having the taste and the fattiness and this and that. So if
you floss and then you eat...
Yeah, but it could sort of be like a לא פלוג. lo
plog. I have to remember, but basically the פוסקים poskim and I
don't remember exactly if the רמב"ם addresses it, but basically the פוסקים
poskim say, you're right, that's sort of what תוספות Tosafot tries to
say that מקנח mekaneach is an alternative. But the פוסקים poskim basically
say, you know, no, it's a type of לא פלוג, lo plog,
that that's enough if the problem is not so big. If the
problem is just the cheese. But if the problem is the meat,
then we don't, we're not going to assume that you're going to
do a good enough job, right.
And then the other question I find interesting is when can you
go against your family מנהג? minhag It seems like his father had
a מנהג minhag because he acted as he was.
Yeah, but you know, but the question is, does every practice that
somebody has as an individual become sort of a family practice or
not? You know, and if it's treated as a חומרא, chumra. not
whatever. Yeah, it is a good question, but right, but you know,
not everything you do has to translate to your family, you know,
could just be a personal חומרא. Okay, but while we are mentioning
מנהג of family practice, I will say, and with this we'll end
and move on, is that interestingly for people that are becoming observant,
the waiting period between meat and milk is for some, I can't
speak for all, is possibly one of the hardest things, believe it
or not. Like keeping שבת, Shabbos, keeping כשרות, Kashrus, okay, you know,
you make those changes in your life. But it's actually true for
us, right? We have to think every time before we're about to
eat meat, about what are we planning on doing the next six
hours? And then we're like, we're restricted for the next six hours.
It's like one of the few things you do that sort of
dictates your future for you. And it can really be a very
heavy burden more than like a lot of things in הלכה. halacha.
So it's actually an interesting question about people that are, you know,
let's say have converted or becoming פרום, frum, and you know, can
you start off at a, at a more lenient practice? You know,
how much do you have to jump straight to the six hours?
Especially if you're converting into an אשכנזי community, and where the practice
is less. You know, some people's principle is you don't want ever
start anybody off slow because then they'll that's where they'll end. You
know, sort of like throw them in the deep end. You gotta
sort of start them off tough. But, but it should be mentioned
that that is a factor, and actually the פוסקים poskim do say
that when there are special considerations like, but this is more like
ad hoc, like somebody is sick, not סכנת נפשות sakanat nefashot or
whatever, but you know, just the doctors sort of say that this
person, you know, should be drinking a lot of dairy products or
whatever, something like that, you know, under those types of circumstances we
can be lenient and go to the sort of other סעודה seuda
position rather than waiting the six hour position. So that is a
position that sometimes can be fallen back on, yes.
What is the problem? Is the problem the stomach or the problem
the teeth?
Ah, that's the debate. Some ראשונים Rishonim say that it's the teeth,
others say that it's more the the fatty stuff that comes up
from the stomach back through the throat that's sort of the fattiness
in the, you know, in the mouth. So that's the debate in
the ראשונים. Rishonim. The גמרא Gemara is unclear. Okay? Let's keep on
going. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to have a little bit
of a digression, or a lot of a digression.
No difference I'm sorry between like lean meat and like fatty meat?
No, there type of, that's a basic לא פלוג. lo plog. Okay,
although whether it's whether it's straight meat or in a dish, in
a mixture, we'll talk about in a minute. Yeah, exactly, talking in
a minute. Okay, so now, now that we said, vinegar the son
of wine, we're going on. אמר שמואל אנא להא מילתא חלא בר
חמרא לגבי אבא. Amar Shmuel ana le-ha milta chala bar chamra legabei
abba. For the following thing, I am like vinegar the son of
wine compared to my father. דאילו אבא הוה סייר נכסיה תרי זימני
ביומא. De-ilu abba hava sayar nichsei terei zimnei beyoma. My father would
go and supervise
and visit his property, you know, his, you know, the his workers
and the fields and make sure everything is is being handled correctly.
He would go and he would do a סיבוב, sivuv, you know,
a what's that called? Not just a visit, but a tour, you
know, he'd check in a site tour twice a day. תרי זימני
ביומא. Trei zimnei beyoma. ואנא לא סיירנא אלא חדא זימנא. Va-ana lo
sayirna ela chada zimna. I only do it once a day. Okay,
so we're not talking about הלכה, halacha, we're just talking about sort
of prudence in regards to your property and in regards to, you
know, to your, to
your money. So, שמואל לטעמיה, Shmuel le-taamei, שמואל Shmuel is going for
his reasoning that this is an important thing, although he didn't do
it as much as his father. דאמר שמואל, De-amar Shmuel, for שמואל
Shmuel said, מאן דסייר נכסיה כל יומא משכח אסתירא, man de-sayar nichsei
kol yoma mishkach astira, anybody who visits his property once a
day will find a coin. Meaning you will be able to discover,
you know, you'll save money, you'll find things that need to be
fixed, you'll be able to to prevent loss. So you'll find some
coins if you go ahead and do it. אביי הוה סייר נכסיה
כל יומא. Abaye hava sayar nichsei kol yoma. אביי Abaye would visit
his property every day. כל יומא ויומא. Kol yoma ve-yoma. יומא חד
פגע באריסיה, Yoma chad paga be-arisei, one day he bumped into his
sharecropper, דדרי פתכא דאופי, de-dari pitcha de-ufei, that he was carrying a
bundle of wood. Basically he was about to take for him himself
a bundle of wood, putting it into like his own car, onto
his own onto his own donkey. אמר ליה, amar lei, yeah, אמר
ליה, amar lei so אביי Abaye said to him, הני להיכא, hanei
le-heicha, oh, where do you think you're taking that? אמר ליה amar
lei לבי מר le-bei mar oh I was taking it to your
house.
So אמר ליה amar lei, so אביי Abaye said to him כבר
קדמוך רבנן kevar kadmucha rabanan the rabbis already beat you to the
punch, meaning because of שמואל’s Shmuel teaching I knew to be here
and therefore I was able to intervene. He didn’t buy the story.
Okay. רב
אסי Rav Assi הוי סייר נכסיה כל יומא havi sayir nichsei kol
yoma רב אסי Rav Assi would visit his property every day.
He said היכא נינו כל הני איסתירא דמר שמואל heicha ninu kol
hanei istira de-mar Shmuel where are all the coins that שמואל Shmuel
promised me? I have, it’s been a lot of effort and I
haven’t gotten anything out of it. So
יומא חד yoma chad one day חזא צינורא דביתקא בארעיה chaza tzinora
de-bitka be-arei he saw a pipe, like a, you know, an irrigation
ditch or whatever, a pipe that was, that had broken forth in
his on his land. It was about to flood his property. שקליה
לגלימיה shaklei le-gelimei it was like the, who was that, the Dutch
boy? Yes, right, he took his cloak כרכיה karchia he wrapped it
up אצייה בגווה atzeiyei be-gavah he stuck it in the hole in
the pipe. רמא קלא rama kala he yelled out for help, for
assistance. אתו אינשי ato inshi everybody came from the town סכרוה sachruha
and they managed to stop it up and to stop it from
flooding.
אשכחטינהו לכולהו איסתירא דמר שמואל ashkechtinu le-chulei istira de-mar Shmuel he found
all of the coins that שמואל Shmuel had promised him. So if
he is to visit your property one day it’ll really be necessary.
It reminds me of something I once read that a mother was
telling her her children like, you know, when I was a young
girl, my mom used to like hide a dollar bill, you know,
in in our room or in the house when she had us
clean the house so that if when we would finally, you know,
clean the house, we’d find we would find the dollar. So her
kid says to says Mom, how come you never did that for
us? She said, I did. Wow.
So they also couldn’t find all the coins of שמואל.
Shmuel.
What?
They didn’t clean well enough to find it. Okay, moving on.
All right, let’s go on.
It’s vinegar the son of wine. It’s a title because of vinegar
the son of wine. Okay, now that we’re talking about cleaning your
hands between meat and milk, or milk and meat depending, we’re going
to talk about washing of the hands, מים ראשונים mayim rishonim and
מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim. Okay, so this is one of the סוגיות
sugyot בש"ס, be-Shas, I mean there’s a whole מסכת masechet about it,
but this is one of the סוגיות sugyot in משניות, mishnayot, but
this is one of the סוגיות sugyot בש"ס be-Shas about מים ראשונים
mayim rishonim מים אחרונים mayim acharonim ידיים. yadayim. So it says אמר
רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב יוסף בר אשי amar Rav Idi
bar Abin amar Rav Yosef bar Ashi מים ראשונים מצוה mayim rishonim
mitzvah the מים ראשונים mayim rishonim that you wash before eating bread
is a מצוה mitzvah ואחרונים חובה ve-acharonim chovah מים אחרונים mayim acharonim
is an obligation. Obligation is understood to mean more weighty than a
מצוה. mitzvah. Why? Because of the concern of as we’ll see מלח
סדומית, Melach Sdomit, the salt that that was handled, they’ll talk about
in a minute, and you could touch your eyes and it could
blind blind you, so it was a health concern and a health
is more weighty than a מצוה. mitzvah. תוספות Tosafot says a נפקא
מינה nafka mina that if you like are in a context of
war and you only have enough water for one, which one you
have to emphasize you have to use the water for, you use
it for the מים אחרונים mayim acharonim because that’s a health issue.
The other difference is that חובה chovah might be obligation but it
lacks the same
religious value as the idea of מצוה. mitzvah. So תוספות Tosafot says
that’s why we make a ברכה bracha on מים ראשונים mayim rishonim
and we don’t make a ברכה bracha on מים אחרונים mayim acharonim
because although they’re a חובה, chovah, they lack a מצוה mitzvah quality
to it. Like it’s not religiously meaningful, right, it’s only done for
health purpose. Okay. So now we’re going to talk about some halakhic
differences.
אמצעי רשות amtzei reshut and the why between, I’m sorry, did I
say the wine? Yes, אמצעי amtzei the last one this, מים ראשונים
ואחרונים חובה, mayim rishonim ve-acharonim chovah, the first and the last are
an obligation, they’re equal weight. אמצעי רשות, amtzei reshut, the middle that
we just do like as we’ll see just for cleanliness purposes you
wash your hands between courses, that’s totally optional. So how come there
we call it a חובה chovah if here you’re calling it a
מצוה? mitzvah? מצוה לגבי רשות חובה קרי ליה mitzvah legabei reshut chovah
karei lei because relative to a רשות reshut as opposed to being
optional, it’s an obligation. But if we’re going to distinguish between the
first and the last, one we’ll call obligatory, the other we’ll call
מצוה, mitzvah, which gives them different valence. Okay, גופא, gufa, let’s look
at that ruling. מים ראשונים ואחרונים חובה, mayim rishonim ve-acharonim chovah, the
first and the last are an obligation, אמצעי רשות, amtzei reshut, the
middle are optional. ראשונים, rishonim, here are the הלכות. halakhot. ראשונים נותנין
בין בכלי בין על גבי קרקע, rishonim notnin bein bi-kli bein al
gabei karka, you can wash it so that the water goes whether
it goes straight on the ground or whether it goes into a
vessel. אחרונים, acharonim, by the way, an important הלכה halakha about going
on the ground on שבת, Shabbos, let’s say for some reason you’re
having a picnic outdoors on שבת Shabbos and you have to wash
your hand, so you can’t wash it directly over the grass because
then you’re watering the grass on שבת, Shabbos, but you actually when
it comes to the issue of watering actually גרמה gerama is allowed.
So if you water it do it
over a concrete, whatever, sidewalk and then it runs off from there
onto the grass, that’s actually okay on שבת. Shabbos. So you can
do it straight on the ground, that’s the מים ראשונים. mayim rishonim.
אחרונים אין נותנין אלא בכלי. acharonim ein notnin ela bi-kli. מים אחרונים
mayim acharonim you cannot do straight on the ground, you have to
do it into a vessel because since it has this מלח סדומית,
Melach Sdomit, right, which is dangerous, then we do not want not
that to be going on the ground. Now the גמרא Gemara too
turns from practical, if you would, medical concerns, health concerns to an
idea also of a רוח רעה Ruach Ra of an evil spirit
that resides over this over on the מלח סדומית Melach Sdomis and
then in the water, so that's also you don't want that evil
spirit on the ground, you put it into a vessel and then
you get rid of it.
Medical concerns, what was the problem?
It's people, other people, will step
in it on the
ground or something, right, something like that. Okay, so ואיכא דאמרי ve-ika
de-amri some say, yeah, some say it's so dangerous, well we'll talk,
I'll talk about that
in a minute.
Let's read a little more.
ואיכא דאמרי ve-ika de-amri others say אין נוטלין על גבי קרקע. ein
nodlin al gabi karka. אין נוטלין על גבי קרקע, ein nodlin al
gabi karka, not it has to be in a vessel, but it
can't be on the ground. מאי בינייהו mai beinaihu from מים אחרונים,
mayim acharonim, what's the difference? Either way you're sort of saying the
same thing. No, איכא בינייהו קינסא. ika beinaihu kinsa. Can you do
it on top of wood chips? It's not in a vessel, but
it's not directly on the ground, it gets absorbed in the wood
chips. So one approach is it has to be a vessel and
you have to remove it to a different location, and the other
is no, it just can't be straight on the ground. מים ראשונים
נוטלים בין בחמין בין בצונן. Mayim rishonim nodlim bein be-chamin bein be-tzonen.
מים ראשונים Mayim rishonim you can use either hot or cold water.
אחרונים אין נוטלים אלא בצונן. Acharonim ein nodlin ela be-tzonen. The מים
אחרונים Mayim Acharonim you have to use cold water, which is a
little ironic, you'd think you'd need hot water to wash it off,
but if it's very hot as we'll talk about in a minute,
then the concern is that it would sort of get, you know,
it would cause the grease or whatever to get, you know, if
you do very hot water but you don't use soap and you
don't, it's not running water also, right? You'd be just pouring it
or whatever, it could actually get the grease more to the surface
without getting rid of it. So that was a concern if it
was hot water for the
אחרונים.
Acharonim. You could use lukewarm, right, not hot.
Right, very hot. We'll talk even how very hot in a minute.
מפני שחמין mipnei she-chamin because the hot water משפים את הידיים, mashpim
es hayadayim, so it gets the hands even more, you know, sort
of, you know, gets the greasy stuff more sort of present on
the surface or רש"י Rashi even says more somehow absorbed in the
hand.
What? Which is opposite of lukewarm.
Oh, that's interesting.
Oh, I didn't think about that. Okay, so maybe there you go,
your pores open. ואין מעבירין את הזוהמא ve-ein maavirin es ha-zuhama and
it's not enough to get rid of the filth. Again, you don't
have running water and you don't have soap. Okay, מים ראשונים נוטלים.
Mayim rishonim nodlim. Now we're going to analyze that about the heat.
מים ראשונים נוטלים בין בחמין בין בצונן. Mayim rishonim nodlim bein be-chamin
bein be-tzonen. אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רב ינאי, Amar Rav
Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rav Yanai, לא שנו אלא שאין היד סולדת
בהן. lo shanu ela she-ein hayad soledes bahen. When is it that
you can use hot water for מים ראשונים? Mayim rishonim? If it's
not יד סולדת. yad soledes. יד סולדת yad soledes is very hot.
יד סולדת yad soledes is if you kept your finger under it
for or in it, let's say, for a few seconds it would
really be hot and you'd have to yank it out. Not immediately,
but if you tried keeping it there for a little while, after
a while it would get too hot and you'd have to yank
it out. That's יד סולדת, yad soledes, whatever that is. They say
it's about, I don't know, 112 degrees or something like that, 105
degrees. Okay, so that hot even
מים ראשונים Mayim rishonim you can't, presumably if it's too hot you
won't do a good job, you won't keep your hands under it,
but not necessarily because it's just going quickly over your hands. So
רש"י Rashi says if it's too hot it doesn't even count anymore
as water. Okay, רש"י Rashi says מחוה, machve, if you look at
רש"י Rashi your hand burns, top רש"י Rashi on עמוד ב'. amud
beis. אם היד סולדת בהן בטלו ונסתלקו מתורת מים. Im hayad soledes
bahen bitlu ve-nistalku mi-toras mayim. That hot is not even considered water,
which is interesting. Okay now,
אבל יד סולדת בהן אין נוטלין. aval yad soledes bahen ein nodlin.
You can't even use it for מים ראשונים Mayim rishonim בהן. bahen.
ואיכא דמתני לה אסיפא Ve-ika de-masni la asseifa some say this is
at the end of the case, the second case. אחרונים אין נוטלים
אלא בצונן. Acharonim ein nodlin ela be-tzonen. The מים אחרונים Mayim Acharonim
you can only use cold water. אבל בחמין לא aval be-chamin lo
not hot water. אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רב ינאי, Amar
Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rav Yanai, לא שנו אלא שיד סולדת
בהן. lo shanu ela she-yad soledes bahen. This is a more lenient
position. Even for the מים אחרונים, Mayim Acharonim, as long as it's
not יד סולדת, yad soledes, hot water you can use.
אבל אין היד סולדת בהן, aval ein hayad soledes bahen, if it's
not יד סולדת, yad soledes, נוטלים, nodlim, you can use for מים
אחרונים. Mayim Acharonim. So there we allow for מים אחרונים Mayim Acharonim
a much wider range, not even lukewarm, even hot as long as
it's not super hot. And then from there we say מכלל דראשונים,
michlal de-rishonim, אף על פי שיד סולדת בהן מותר, af al pi
she-yad soledes bahen mutar, which means that מים ראשונים Mayim rishonim even
יד סולדת. yad soledes. Well, why would you want to
use
that as you know?
Alright, that's you happen to have it heated up and you're not
going to drink from it or use it in your in your
meal, whatever you're going to make. Okay. Okay, now. Now we're going
to say ומים אמצעיים רשות. u-mayim emtzoyim reshus. Now the middle washing
we do between between courses, that's totally optional. אמר רב נחמן לא
שנו אלא בין תבשיל לתבשיל. Amar Rav Nachman lo shanu ela bein
tavshil le-tavshil. Let's just between one, let's say, cooked dish and another.
אבל בין תבשיל לגבינה, aval bein tavshil le-gevina, and תבשיל tavshil normally
means meat. If it's some type of a meat stew and then
cheese, חובה, chova, then you have to wash your hands. Now this
is the last line. So I lied before when I said it
was the last thing about meat and milk waiting. This line is
the last line. This says that between a meat dish and a
milk dish just wash your hands, you have to wash your hands,
which sort of sounds like you don't have to wait for say
a different meal at all or you... have to do is wash
your hands, even though meat is first, and תוספות Tosafot says you're
right that it basically does say that and once again we're seeing
that, you know, sometimes even a small division suffices. Now I want
to point out, if the concern were, again, about a practical reality
of, you know, the meatiness and the fattiness or whatever, it's not
exactly clear, but you could say it's a little, it is a
difference when it's in a stew. But again, it's not exactly clear
why it should make such a difference, when it's in a stew
as opposed to when it's direct. But again, if it's the concern
about what it seems to be like eating it together, then when
the thing is, you know, is there by itself, it's a little
more standing out that you're having meat and milk together than when
it's hidden in the middle of a stew. If that weren't clear
enough, I want to read the next line. No.
Oh, no, no, I'm sorry, not the next line. And if that
weren't enough, then the, the question is about why it makes... okay,
so anyway, תוספות Tosafot also thinks it's not clear in the גמרא,
Gemara, but תוספות Tosfos, also thinks when it says between תבשיל tavshil
and תבשיל tavshil you don't have to, that means even if the
first תבשיל tavshil is a meat stew and the second תבשיל tavshil
is a milkish stew, that even there you don't have to. The
only time you have to is if when it's a meat stew
and then the milk is in its... is direct, is בעין. be'eyn.
Now again, who the heck cares? If the need for washing is
to remove what you ate beforehand, who cares if the second thing
is direct cheese, cheese בעין, be'eyn, or cheese in the... in a
stew? Either way, you know, how does that affect getting rid of
what's happened before, what's coming up now? So the difference here between
whether the stuff is in its own form or buried in the
middle of a stew and that we make these distinctions that it's
not so bad if it was in a stew beforehand and then
just wash your hands, and if it's a stew afterwards then also
you don't even need anything, etc. Once again, I think this points
to the issue that it's not just about the reality of what's
in your hand and what's in your mouth, it's about the experience
of having them together. And the more that's hidden and they're in
some type of a stew, the less of a problem it is.
So the actual הלכה halacha that emerges from here is that technically
speaking, you know, let's say somebody eats something that actually is not
the OU-D, which half the time is dairy equipment and not dairy.
Somebody eats something that's really OU-D, somebody actually eats something that is
מילכיג, milchig, but, you know, okay, it's מילכיג milchig or not... maybe
מילכיג, milchig, פליישיג. fleishig. You right, you go into a restaurant and
it says a פליישיג fleishig restaurant, כל הכלים בחזקת בשרי, kol hakeilim
bechezkat besari, you know, all the dishes are to be assumed to
be פליישיג fleishig even if they're פארווע parve dishes. Why? Because okay,
there's grease, there's whatever going on. I guess you have to assume
that it's פליישיג. fleishig. But do I have to wait six hours
now? So of course we say yes. But really, according to this,
if it's just פליישיג fleishig taste and it's תבשיל tavshil or whatever,
it's just washing your hands, maybe cleaning out your mouth, as long
as it's not the פליישיג fleishig is בעין. be'eyn. So again, that
is מעיקר הדין, me'ikar hadin, that's really the case, but again in
שולחן ערוך we flatten all of these differences and we say you
always wait six hours regardless. But again here, besides the issue before
that maybe washing is enough, maybe a different meal is enough without
the six hours, we might be saying always six hours when meat
is first, here we're seeing that actually if it's in some type
of a mixture, it might not really be required any wait. It's
pretty clear from this גמרא, Gemara, although תוספות Tosfos tries to have
one read that gets out of it and nevertheless we sort of,
you know, ignore that for practical purposes.
And it's very interesting what you said, so is it the anything...
as opposed to dairy equipment where you don't really care, if it's
meat equipment then you do care just because we're concerned with all
the other things with meat, is that...
is that what... No, I'm saying forget meat equipment, let's say that
there's a real concern, you go into a פליישיג fleishig restaurant and
you order, you know, the French fries. So there's a real concern
that some פליישיג fleishig grease got onto it or whatever, I mean
sometimes דווקא davka they even cook it in פליישיג fleishig grease, right,
because that's fattier and it's better, you know, let's say you actually
did that, right, you went ahead and they actually cooked it in
the grease that they use to cook the meat or whatever and
they cooked it in the פליישיג fleishig grease. It has a really
nice meaty taste, these French fries. Okay, I think they do that
in non-kosher restaurants with lard beef fat. Anyway, so technically speaking, that's
תבשיל, א תבשיל בשרי. tavshil, a tavshil besari. Now you want to
eat מילכיג milchig afterwards, all you have to do is wash your
hands.
No, I'm talking about cooking it in פליישיג fleishig equipment but it's
not פליישיג fleishig grease.
No, no, no, that...
no,
that's not even a... yeah, that's not even the issue.
Okay, yeah, anything cooked when it's cooked in מילכיג milchig dishes or
פליישיג fleishig dishes that are clean, you do not have to wait.
Yes.
Okay, and then...
That's actual practical הלכה. halacha. Yes.
So you're saying that somehow if it's a תבשיל tavshil it's less
considered eating it together? Yep. No, but if you have a stew
you'd say that that's not eating... I don't...
I'm just saying that if I had it before, it's not having
it right now at the same table, I had it at my
previous... my previous dish was that type of a dish. The experience
of meat and milk together is a lot less when... it's a
lot more when I have a steak and then I have cheese,
as opposed to if first I have a dish that has a
little bit of פליישיג fleishig cooked into it and now I have
another dish.
You don't think a meat like a goulash is mostly stuff... Yeah,
that...
yeah, that might be right, saying stew was a little misleading. I
agree. What's considered בעין be'eyn or not, if you have big chunks
of meat, that's... that might very well...
You're talking about like a chicken...
Yeah, somehow that it's more... yeah, it's not exactly clear where to
draw the line. Yes.
Good question of...
practical practical practical question
if I'm purchasing something like let's say vegetarian liver at a גלאט
glatt shop or I'm purchasing these broccoli soufflés that say
they're made in meat כלים kelim but there's no meat in it.
So if they right.
So we haven't learned that סוגיא yet which is what but I
will give you an answer which is that if something is made
in meat כלים kelim and they tell you there is no you
know it wasn't cooked at the same time with meat and there
wasn't meat juices flying around just meat כלים kelim then you are
not you are not פליישיג. fleishig. You do not have to eat
it with מילכיגס? milchigs? No we we פסקן pasken you don't eat
it directly with מילכיגס milchigs but you can eat מילכיגס milchigs directly
afterwards. If בדיעבד bedie'avad you mixed it with מילכיגס milchigs then בדיעבד
bedie'avad actually we allow you to to eat the thing. But לכתחילה
lechatchila we don't allow you to eat it together with yes.
And I just thought that with clean כלים kelim if it was
a פליישיג fleishig pot from בלוע balua and נותן טעם noten ta'am
and
is that just a is that a is that a real...
נותן טעם בר נותן טעם דהיתרא noten ta'am bar noten ta'am de'heteira
because since it's all היתר heter if it were non-כשר kosher כלים
kelim yes it'd be a problem. Since it's all היתר heter it's
מילכיגס milchigs or פליישיגס fleishigs but it's all היתר heter it's all
permissible then the principle is that two degrees removed from the meat
into the pot and from the pot into the dish if the
dish is פרווה parve not if the dish is מילכיג. milchig. If
the dish is מילכיג milchig when it comes out of the pot
into the dish it makes it טרייף. treif. But if the dish
is פרווה parve the קוגל kugel and it's two degrees removed and
it's היתר heter that's called נותן טעם בר נותן טעם דהיתרא noten
ta'am bar noten ta'am de'heteira and therefore practically speaking it's like it
doesn't exist. Okay but we'll talk about that later. Okay moving on.
Okay now we are going to spend the rest of the דף
daf with מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim. Ha so much for my thinking
we'd get caught up. All right so אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב
חייא מפני מה אמרו מים אחרונים חובה Amar Rav Yehuda bereih de-Rav
Chiya mipnei mah ameru mayim acharonim chova why did they say that
the מים אחרונים mayim acharonim is an obligation? So we're going to
now focus in on מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim. שמלח סדומית יש she-melach
Sedomit yesh there is this salt of סדום. Sedom. I'll talk about
what that means in a minute. שמסמא את העיניים she-mesama et ha-einayim
it can blind the eyes. אמר אביי ומשתכח כקורטא בכורא Amar Abaye
u-mishtakach ke-kurta be-kora so here's Dov's question. It's only a tiny percentage
it's like a one tiny little kernel in a huge כור. kor.
A כור kor is like you know
whatever gallon a barrel
you know one part per thousand but nevertheless because of its presence
it is very dangerous. Now what is מלח סדומית? melach Sedomit?
Because the גמרא Gemara speaks about all of these dangers.
I'm going to talk about the רוח רעה ruach ra'a etc. People
and the word סדום Sedom obviously is evocative because of the whole
story with לוט Lot or whatever. People tend to think that it's
talking about some very you know mysterious powerful whatever mystical salt. But
technically speaking מלח סדומית melach Sedomit is sea salt and it's contracted
from מלח מסחורתית melach mischartit I forget exactly how I pronounce it
which is mineral salt. So though you'll understand why we refer to
sea salt as סדום Sedom סדומית Sedomit because of the you know
Dead Sea. But actually that's what it really just means is sea
salt but anyway the גמרא Gemara did say that it was very
powerful. Now why as you're well aware I assume תוספות Tosfos says
that in nowadays we don't bother it because we don't have this
we don't bother with מים אחרונים mayim acharonim we don't have this
מלח סדומית. melach Sedomit. What is תוספות Tosafot really talking about why
is it different? I had a theory which was...
you wanted to say that?
Yeah although sadly I think it's been proven incorrect but somehow I'll
have to manipulate the facts to make it correct. My theory was
that why do you wash your hands? Why do your hands get
so salty? Because your meat is preserved in salt with a ton
of salt. You're handling the meat right and then it's you're not
washing your hands you're going to get it into your eyes. Okay
so that was the גמרא's Gemara concern. What was the reality in
תוספות's time? So not just today they also preserved their meat in
salt right? So number one is first of all they lived in
colder climates. So I'm not so sure that this is another theory
I have to see if I can prove or not I have
no idea I'm not so sure they needed to preserve it in
the same amount of salt if it's a colder climate. They had
to preserve it but maybe not to the same degree you know
maybe also long period of winter maybe they didn't have to preserve
it at all you just put outside in the snow I don't
know. That's number one. But number two is I had a theory
that in תוספות's time was when forks were introduced because actually right
the normally they would directly eat things they had knives you couldn't
cut something you had spoons but who needs a fork? You know
you just put it with your hands into your mouth. And actually
when forks were first introduced in Europe there was you know there
were a lot of actually you know priests and religious figures were
very much against it. They said if God had wanted us to
use forks He wouldn't have given us fingers.
So forks was actually a major invention. I mean sometimes you have
like a like a large fork that you turn something on a
fire but as something that you normally eat use for your meal
was a major so my theory was was that it happened after
they introduced forks and their hands weren't getting directly handling it. Sadly
however I think the forks were introduced in France and Germany around
the 13th 14th century which is after when תוספות was writing so
I'm still going to try to prove it though. It's close enough
that maybe I can maybe there's a way that I can prove
that. Anyway but what?
They had the three fork they had right the prototype version of
the fork. They had
the...
Yeah, well, that was another theory. Maybe they went, when did they
introduce napkins? That's the question, too. Later than forks? I mean when
I first went to Israel, I don't know if this is still
the practice 20 years ago in ישיבה, Yeshiva, I was shocked. No
napkins.
They just had like, Netila was scarce.
Right, so you just wash your hands, you don't have napkins. Anyway,
whatever reason they did it for תוספות, but it seems like unless
the גמרא Gemara does mean something mystical, the simple meaning of the
גמרא Gemara is the sea salt which presumably they would preserve their
food in. It would get on your hands, get to your eyes,
that's the problem.
And so you wash between them, you use the same sea salt
then, you do it between courses at a סעודה. seudah.
Yeah, but because you're not, no, once you're in the meal you're
focused on eating the food. Your hands aren't just wandering all over.
When you're done with the meal, that's when we can't control where
your hands go.
You see תוספות was to not do?
He said, no, he said we don't do the practice and he
said the way he justified it is because we don't have מלח
סדומית. Melach Sedomis. Okay.
תוספות didn't live near the sea, like in France there's...
I don't know, he... yeah, I don't even know if, maybe he
translated מלח סדומית Melach Sedomis as something else, but the point is
he was working post-facto. The practice was not to do it, he
had to find a way to justify it. Okay, maybe it just
meant we didn't preserve our stuff in sea salt. I don't know.
It is a good point though, you're right, France probably has a
lot of sea salt. Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב
אשי: Amar lei Rav Achai brei deRava leRav Ashi: כל מלחא דכיל
מלחא. Kal milcha d'chil milcha. There's actually an interesting מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes
Rishonim what this phrase means, but anyway, generally it's assumed to mean
כיל kal which means to measure. If you measured salt, okay, meaning
you didn't eat salt, you just handled it,
you were
measuring. Okay, but it wasn't in your in your in your food.
מה, Ma, what's the הלכה? halakha? Do you have to wash your
hands? אמר ליה לא מבעיא. Amar lei lo mibaya. No, then it's
not necessary. Actually, לא מבעיא lo mibaya is a dangerous phrase because
לא מבעיא lo mibaya could mean, ah, you don't even have to
ask that question, it's obvious, or it could mean you don't need
to. I'm curious, what does
our friend Rabbi Schorr say about לא מבעיא? lo mibaya? Does he
say not necessary or...
There is no question that you need to.
That's certainly more. Right. All right, anyway, there is a debate in
the ראשונים Rishonim how to read this phrase.
Okay. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: מרישא הוה אמינא: Me-resha hava amina: האי
דלא משו מיא בתראי על ארעא, Hai d'lo mashu maya batrai al
ara, originally I said the reason that you cannot do מים אחרונים
mayim achronim directly on the ground, remember we said that, משום זוהמא,
mishum zuhama, was because of filth. Meaning either because it's dangerous, it'll
still have that מלח סדומית, Melach Sedomis, or even if you've washed
it away and dissolved that salt, it's disgusting. Who needs your greasy
water from washing your hands on the ground that somebody else can
walk into? So that's why we didn't do it. אמר לי מר,
Amar lei Mar, the master, if you look at the side that's
רבה, Rabba, said to me: משום דשריא רוח רע עלייהו. mishum de-sharya
ruach ra alaihu. No, it's because of the evil spirit. And now
we're going to have a fascinating passage of the גמרא Gemara where
אביי Abaye basically says, I originally thought some very practical explanations for
a lot of practices, things that would resonate with us, things that
make a lot of practical sense, but רבה Rabba told me that
it was all due to concerns about various spirits and more types
of other-worldly concerns.
So he put it in like a pit though, right?
Well, if you covered it up, maybe. All right. ואמר אביי: V'amar
Abaye: מרישא הוה אמינא: Me-resha hava amina: האי דלא שקיל מינא דפתורא
כי נקיט איניש כסא למשתי. Hai d'lo shakil mina d'potura ki nakit
inish kasa l'mishtei. The fact that when somebody is about to take
a cup to drink, you don't remove something from the table in
front of him. Like there he is, he's drinking his cup and
the waiter's coming to remove the dish. What was a פתורא? potura?
A dish. Okay. שמא יארע דבר קלקלה בסעודה, Shema ye-arei davar kalkala
bi-seudah, because maybe he's going to say, wait, I'm in the middle
of eating that, don't take it away, and he's going to try
to talk as he's drinking and he's going to choke on his
drink. Very nice practical explanation. אמר לי מר, Amar lei Mar, the
master רבה Rabba told me, no: משום דקשיא לרוח צרדא. mishum d'kasha
l'ruach tzerada. It will bring the spirit צרדא Tzerada if you do
this type of behavior. This is a spirit that presumably was the
cause of epilepsy. So it'll that type of behavior opens you up
to epilepsy based on opening you up to this evil spirit, and
that's why we don't do it.
Does צרדא Tzerada mean epilepsy?
I have no idea because רש"י Rashi says it means אסטרודיסין, astrodissin,
so maybe somebody knows Old French, but I know it because I
looked it up in Jastrow.
I have no idea how they identified it.
Is it about the eater or the person cleaning up?
No, the eater. The eater. ולא אמרן אלא דשקיל ולא מהדר. V'lo
amaran ela d'shakil v'lo mahadar.
That's only if you took the dish away and didn't put it
back. אבל שקיל ומהדר לית לן בה. Aval shakil u-mehadar leit lan
ba. But if you took and returned it, not a problem. ולא
אמרן אלא חוץ לארבע אמות. V'lo amaran ela chutz l'arba amos. It's
only when you remove the dish outside of ארבע אמות arba amos
from the person eating. אבל תוך ארבע אמות לית לן בה, Aval
toch arba amos leit lan ba, within ארבע אמות arba amos it's
not a problem. ולא אמרן אלא מידי דצריך לסעודתא. V'lo amaran ela
midi d'tzarich l'seudasa. And it's only a problem if you remove something
from his presence that's needed for the סעודה. seudah. אבל מידי דלא
צריך לסעודתא לית לן בה, Aval midi d'lo tzarich l'seudasa leit lan
ba, but if it's not part of the סעודה, seudah, it's not
a problem. Wait one minute, you'll tell me in a minute. מר
בר רב אשי קפיד אפילו אאסיטא ובוכנא דתבלי. Mar bar Rav Ashi
kapi afilu a-asita v'buchna d'tavli. He even did not let them remove
from his presence the mortar and pestle of spices. Basically like the
salt shaker. So it's not only removing food, actually that was an
empty mortar and pestle, so even if it's not removing food but
removing the type of. dishes that you might want to use during
the meal, because you might want to bring some spices and grind
some spices to put on your dish. For him, even that was
a problem because, again, of this exposing you to this spirit.
Yeah, and okay, it's sorry, it's
not
epilepsy.
Yeah, I don't know, Jesse said that's epilepsy. Moving on. Okay.
One second, one second. Wikipedia. מידי דצריכי לסעודתא midi d'tzrichi l'seudasa because
they're needed for the meal. Yes?
Story in the Middle Ages with the French, when they decided enough
with wiping your face on the tablecloth, they gave people
spoons first.
What time?
Middle Ages is not good enough for me.
Ah, way too late. Middle Ages is 1300 something.
Yeah, but for תוספות it's important, because if that's the factor, I
want it to be like around 12th century.
I know with the facts where I want the facts to get.
Let's see if we can ready them.
All right, anyway, fine. Okay. מר בר רב אשי קפיד. Mar bar
Rav Ashi kafid. Oh, we did that. Okay. ואמר אביי, v'amar Abaye,
אביי Abaye said, right by the line on top of the ג'
ע"א gimel amud aleph in the right corner column, the word אביי,
Abaye, first word of the line. ואמר אביי, v'amar Abaye, רישא הוה
אמינא, reisha hava amina, I used to say, האי דכנשי נשוורא, hai
d'kanshei nashvara, the fact that we sweep up the crumbs, משום נקיותא,
mishum nakiuta, for cleanliness purposes. Yeah,
that makes sense. ואמר לי מר, v'amar li Mar, as the master
said to me, משום דקשי לעניותא, mishum d'kashi l'aniyuta, no, having crumbs
on your ground and not cleaning them up is a will expose
you to the whatever spirit it is that brings about poverty. So
therefore you do it to prevent poverty.
Practically you have to do it.
But what? I don't know. ההוא גברא, hahu gavra, now we'll have
a little story. There was a man דהוה מהדר עליה שר דעניותא,
d'hava mehadar alei sar d'aniyuta, the spirit of poverty was trying to
catch this person, was trying to, you know, he was trying to
seize them and make this person poor. I don't know who sent
this
master of poverty on its mission, but it had a mission to
make this person poor. ולא הוה יכיל ליה, v'lo hava yachil lei,
he was not able to find an opening because דזהיר אנשוורא טובא,
d'zahir a'nashvara tuva, he was very careful
about crumbs. יומא חד כריך ריפתא אגילא, yoma chad karich rifta agila,
one day he was having a picnic, he was having bread on
top of grass. אמר,
השתא ודאי נפל בידי, hashta vadai nafal b'yadi, now I'm gonna get
him, because how is he gonna be careful with crumbs at a
picnic? And
apparently he did not lay out a picnic blanket. Okay. בתר דאכל,
basar d'achal, after he ate, אייתי מרא, aitei mara, he took a
shovel, this
man, עקרינהו akrinhu all of the grass from that space that had
all the crumbs in it, שדנהו לנהרא, shadinhu l'nahara, and threw it
into the river. So there should not be the crumbs that had
fallen there should not remain there.
He's OCD. שמעיה דקאמר, shameia d'ka'amar, this man heard a voice saying,
it was the voice of the spirit, וי דאפקינהו האי גברא מביתיה,
vai d'afkinhu hai gavra m'beiteih, woe that this man, meaning referring to
himself, I the spirit, have been kicked out of my house. Meaning
I can't do my job, I can't get to this guy, he's
too careful. Okay. ואמר אביי, v'amar Abaye, so that's that. ואמר אביי,
v'amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said, רישא הוה אמינא, reisha hava amina, I
used to say, האי דלא שתי אופיא, hai d'lo shatei ufiya, that
that you don't drink foam on the top of a
glass, משום מיאוסא, mishum miusa, because it's disgusting.
ואמר לי מר, v'amar li Mar,
very practical, so the master, רבה, Raba, said to me, no, משום
דקשי לכרצם, mishum d'kashi l'kartzem, because it causes runny noses basically. Okay,
so it's difficult for, meaning it causes you to have the problem
of like of a runny nose.
Look how practical.
It gets in your nose.
Oh, yeah.
That's true. Maybe this was less about spirit. משתי קשי לכרצם, mishtei
kashi l'kartzem, if you drink foam, it's bad, but we'll see other
things can't be read that way. It's bad for the runny nose.
מנפח בה קשי לרישא, minpach beh kashi l'reisha, if you blow the
foam off,
then that is bad for your head, will give you a headache.
מדחי לה קשי לעניותא, madchei lah kashi l'aniyuta, if you push it
off with your hand,
then that'll expose you for poverty. It is true that the things
that expose you for poverty are a type of a mistreatment of
food and of like maybe these
crumbs, the foam, so maybe you know it's somewhat symbolically, although I
don't know if the גמרא Gemara meant it symbolically could be understood,
you know, it's sort of like before יעקב Yaakov went back for
the פכים קטנים, pachim ktanim, that if you're not
careful even about the small things, you show a certain
disregard, then that sort of symbolic
about deserving of poverty, you know, that you have to pay attention
even especially things that are food which are the livelihood is
dependent on. Okay, anyway, מאי תקנתיה, mai takanteih, what should you do
if you went ahead and drank it and whatever and got sick
or got a runny nose?
So לשקויי שקויי, l'shakuei shakuei, let it
settle, there's nothing to be done, wait for it to settle down
or push it
off. Oh, that's true, yeah, that could be, that actually could be
what it means. If you put something in it, will it cause
the foam to settle?
If you drop something into the glass and sit there and wait.
Oh, that's true, yeah, that actually does it for some reason. So
maybe that is what it means. Okay, now, לכירסם Lekarsam if you
did get this runny
nose? לכירסם דחמרא Lekarsam de-chamra if you got it as a result
of drinking the foam off of wine, שכרא Shichra you should drink
beer.
דשכרא מאי Deshichra mai if you drank the if you got this
כירסם karsam by drinking the foam of beer, what should you do?
דשכרא מיא. Deshichra maya. If you got the foam by drinking beer,
then drink water. The water will be an antidote to this this
runny nose you got from drinking the foam of beer. דמיא Demaya
if you drank the if you drank the foam of water, you
know, like in New York sometimes you get bubbly water or whatever,
anyway, and then what do you do to fix that problem if
you drank the foam of water? לית ליה תקנתא Leis lei takanta
there's no way to fix it. Okay, you're going to have your
runny nose. והיינו דאמרי אינשי V'hainu d'amri inshi that's what people say,
בתר עניא אזלא עניותא Batar anya azla anyuta poverty follows the poor.
The poor get poorer, the rich get richer, so water which is
the poorest of drinks, that is the one that brings about you
know these problems and that can't be fixed. Okay, but again it
is interesting, this disregard of even these sort of less important foods,
somehow that is what's tied into this idea of poverty. ואמר אביי
V'amar Abaye Abaye used to say, מריש הוה אמינא Me-reish hava amina
I used to say, האי דלא אכלי ירקא מכישא דאסרי גינאה Hai
d'lo achli yarka mikisha d'asri ginai the fact that you don't eat
a vegetable straight out of the bundle. You come back with let's
say I don't know a bundle of carrots and what you do
is normally you open up the bundle and you you know you
chop up the carrots but you don't pull the carrot straight out
of the bundle and eat it straight from the bundle. So why
not? So I used to
say משום דמיחזי כרעבתנותא Mishum demichzei keravtanuta it looks like you're starving,
you know, you know it's not דרך ארץ Derech eretz you wait,
you undo it, you know what you brought up in a barn
you know okay so you know you don't do it like you
know it looks like you're overly overly ravenous. אמר ליה מר Amar
lei Mar Mar said no, משום דקשי לכשפים Mishum dekashi lachshafim it
exposes you to witchcraft. This is the type of thing that makes
you vulnerable to witchcraft. Now we're going to have a witchcraft story.
רב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא Rav Chisda ve-Rabba bar Rav Huna
Rav Chisda and Rabba bar Rav Huna הוו קאזלי בארבא Hava ka-azli
be-arba they were going in a boat. אמרה להו ההיא מטרוניתא Amra
lehu hahi matrunita a certain matron, woman, said to them, non-Jewish woman
that's a name sometimes used maybe a Roman non-Jewish woman except Rav
Chisda and Rabba bar Rav Huna were in בבל. Bavel. Anyway, a
certain matron said to them, אותבן בהדייכו Otvan bahadaichu let me sit
with you. לא אותבוה Lo otvua they didn't want her to sit
with them. Maybe they were afraid she would do witchcraft as she
eventually does, maybe they're having a private conversation you know, maybe they
they said get behind the מחיצה Mechitza I don't know what they
said but anyway they didn't want her to sit with them. לא
אותבוה. Lo otvua. אמרה מילתא Amra milta so she said a magic
word, some incantation right? Some incantation. אסרתא לארבא Asarta le-arba she caused
the boat to stop, sort of like a little bit like the
Jonah story we just read. Okay, so the boat got you know
couldn't go forward. אמרו אינהו מילתא Amru inhu milta they said an
opposite word, שריוה Sharyua they made the boat they allowed the boat
to move. Now the question is who allows them to to do
witchcraft? So Rashi says well maybe it was a שם השם Shem
Hashem but Rashi says it doesn't sound like that wasn't witchcraft I
don't know. Then Rashi
then Rashi also suggests that no you know you're in danger when
you're in a boat that's stuck so maybe they were allowed to
do it because of the danger. But it still raises interesting questions
like we had before about סימנים Simanim etc. you know חז"ל Chazal
that really believed in the efficacy of this stuff and sometimes even
you know as we see and sometimes even did certain things like
סימנים Simanim saying these magic words whatever, where do you draw the
line between what was considered permissible and what was biblically forbidden forms
of these?
I have a new theory though.
What?
I was restoring the natural order maybe. But you're still using witchcraft,
yes.
By the 12th century, yes, the custom of using table linens was
almost universal throughout France.
Excellent! That's a better explanation than the fork now. If
they had napkins... Okay, smart napkins.
Right? And they didn't sit in a place, they hung from the
table and they were used by more than one person.
Interesting. Okay but now I'll use my napkin explanation instead of my
fork one. Alright let's finish this story, it's already pretty late. Okay,
so they said something שריוה Sharyua they made the boat keep on
going, they permitted they released the boat. אמרה להו Amra lehu so
she said to them, מאי אעביד לכו Mai a-avid lechu what can
I do to you דלא מכתחיתו בחספא D'lo mictachitu be-chaspa because you
do not expose yourself to witchcraft? You don't do any of the
practices that would make people vulnerable to witchcraft. Here are the practices,
don't do these. Number one, דלא מכתחיתו בחספא D'lo mictachitu be-chaspa you
don't wipe yourself in the bathroom with pottery. Okay, if you use
anything that's that can be אושלט בהן Oshlet bahen
then it's exposes you that that is flammable exposes you to witchcraft.
That's why the גמרא Gemara used rocks, I don't know how we
now use paper, anyway. ולא קטליתו כינה אמאנייכו V'lo katlitu kina amanaichu
you do not kill lice on your clothes. If you smush the
lice on your clothes as opposed to removing them and killing them
elsewhere that exposes you. ולא אכליתו ירקא מכישא דאסרי גינאה V'lo achlitu
yarka mikisha d'asri ginai and you don't eat a vegetable from the
bundle that the gardener wrapped together. together. So therefore you, I can't
do anything, you do not expose yourself. Let's just read one more.
I know it's already 8:30, but just one more. ואמר אביי מרישא
הוינא אמינא, ve'amar Abbaye mereisha havina amina, I used to say, האי
דלא אכלי ירקא דנפל אפתחא, hai delo achli yarka denafal atacha, the
fact that you don't eat a vegetable that falls on the tray,
משום מאיסותא, mishum meisuta,
it's disgusting, it fell off of your plate, and I don't know.
אמרה לי אם, amra li em, my mother said, משום דקשי לריח
הפה. mishum dekashi lerei'ach hapa. No, somehow because once it's on the
plate it causes bad
breath. ואמר אביי מרישא הוינא אמינא, ve'amar Abbaye mereisha havina amina, האי
דלא יתבי תותי
מרזיבא, hai delo yatev tutei marziva, that you don't sit under a
what do you call it, a drain pipe, pipe, משום שופכין, mishum
shofchin, because you don't want the water to spill on you. אמרה
לי אם, amra li em, yeah, like a gutter, like a rain
gutter from the roof. אמרה לי אם, amra li em, my mother
said, משום דשכיחי מזיקין. mishum deshichichi mazikin. No, it because because that's
where the מזיקין, mazikin, the dangerous spirits, hang out under there and
you don't want to be exposed to them. And this is the
last case we'll read. הנהו שקולאי, hanehu shkulai, there were certain schleppers,
so it goes, it's a very honorable vocation, it's already in the
גמרא, Gemara, schleppers, דהוו דרו חביתא דחמרא, dehavu daru chavita dechamra, they
were carrying a barrel of wine, בעו לאתפוחי, ba'u leitpuchi, they wanted
to take a break, a rest, אותבוה תותי מרזיבא, otvuha tutei marziva,
they put it underneath a drain pipe, underneath a rain gutter, פקעה,
paka'a, it exploded. אתו לקמיה דמר בר רב אשי atu lekamei deMar
bar Rav Ashi because they because basically the spirit under the drain
pipe destroyed it. So they came to מר בר רב אשי. Mar
bar Rav Ashi. אפקיה שיפורא, apkei shipura, he took out a shofar,
שמתיה, shamtei, he put this spirit under חרם. cherem. So okay, somehow
the חרם cherem of rabbis is effective even for these evil spirits.
He shouldn't have done it. אתא לקמיה, ata lekamei, so the spirit
came to מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi and asked
for a דין תורה. din Torah. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said
to him, אמאי עבדת הכי, amai avdat hachi, why are you doing
this to me? אמר
ליה,
amar
lei, he said, היכי אעביד, heichi aeivid, דאותביה באודנאי, deotveih be'odnai,
what should I have done? They put it right in my ear.
I was sleeping under that drain pipe. They put this barrel of
wine right in my ear. What did you expect me to do?
Why are you blaming me? אמר ליה, amar lei, את בדוכתא דשכיחי
רבים מאי בעית. at beduchta deshichichi rabim mai bayit.
No, you should not be in a place where the masses are.
You should go be lying down and taking your nap somewhere else.
That was not, you did not belong
there. איהו דשנית, ihu deshannit, you did the wrong thing, you did
something different that you took your nap there where it is a
public space. זיל שלים, zil shalleim, you have to go pay these
people for the barrel you broke. אמר ליה, amar lei, השתא נמי
ליתן לי מר זימנא דאפרע. hashta nami litein li Mar zimna de'efra.
Give me some time and I'll pay them back because what he's
going to do is the spirit steals other people's goods and so
therefore he's going to steal goods from other people. I don't know
how that was allowed. And I will pay them back.
How else would he make money?
קבע ליה זימנא, keva lei zimna, he gave him a time, כי
מטא זימנא איעכב, ki mata zimna i'akkev, when the time came he
was delayed. כי אתא אמר ליה, ki ata amar lei, when he
came, whoever it was said to him, מר בר רב אשי Mar
bar Rav Ashi said to him, אמאי לא אתית בזמנך, amai lo
atit bezimnach, why did you not come at the right time? אמר
ליה, כל מילי, kol milli, because דצייר וכייל וחתים ומני, detsayar vechayil
vechatim umani, anything that is either bound or knotted up or measured
or counted, לית לן רשותא למשקל מיניה, leit lan reshuta lemishkal mineih,
I can't steal from people. I can only steal from people stuff
that is, you know, basically they're mistreating again. They're not counting, they
don't know how much it is, they're not protecting it. That's the
stuff that we have access to and I had to find that
stuff so that I could pay these guys back. עד דמשכחינן מידי
דהפקירא, ad demishkachinan midi dehefkeira, until we find something that is either
ownerless or sounds like basically treated as ownerless. So again you have
the idea that the mistreating of food or whatever or mistreating of
objects is what exposes you to these spirits. I think we will
end here. Okay.
Paperness
that began in 19